Guide to the Berton W. Crandall Proof Album collection
Stanford University. Libraries.
Department of Special Collections and University Archives
Berton W Crandall proof album collection
1904-1930
PC0003
Crandall, Berton W., 1882-1979.
12.42 Linear feet (18 albums)
Proof albums assembled by Crandall of photograph taken during the year to be browsed by patrons of his Palo Alto studio. Crandall concentrated primarily on Stanford athletics and student activities. Sports most heavily documented are football, track, and baseball; others include crew, swimming, basketball, gymnastics, and polo. There are a few photographs of women's crew, track, and basketball teams. Student activities include the Frosh-Soph Tie-Up, student parades, initiations of the honor society Skull & Snakes and the Press Club, dances, plays, Plug Ugly events, junior day activities on Lake Lagunita, and commencement processions. Special events documented include John C. Branner's inauguration as Stanford University President, 1913; and the Student Army Training Corps, 1916-1917.
Department of Special Collections and University Archives Green Library 557 Escondido Mall Stanford, CA 94305-6064 Email: specialcollections@stanford.edu Phone: (650) 725-1022 URL: http://library.stanford.edu/spc
Administrative Information
Provenance
Gift of Berton W. Crandall.
Information about Access
This collection is open for research.
Biographical/Historical Sketch
Berton W. Crandall moved with his family to Palo Alto in 1898 from Pompey, New York, where he had been born in 1882. After graduating from Palo Alto High School, he attended Stanford University, earning his bachelor’s degree in chemistry in January 1907. A professional photographer, he also owned and operated a photography store on University Avenue in Palo Alto. He died in May of 1979.
Description of the Collection
Proof albums assembled by Crandall of photograph taken during the year to be browsed by patrons of his Palo Alto studio. Crandall concentrated primarily on Stanford athletics and student activities. Sports most heavily documented are football, track, and baseball; others include crew, swimming, basketball, gymnastics, and polo. There are a few photographs of women's crew, track, and basketball teams. Student activities include the Frosh-Soph Tie-Up, student parades, initiations of the honor society Skull & Snakes and the Press Club, dances, plays, Plug Ugly events, junior day activities on Lake Lagunita, and commencement processions. Special events documented include John C. Branner's inauguration as Stanford University President, 1913; and the Student Army Training Corps, 1916-1917.
Arrangement
Albums organized by year
photographs arranged by negative number within each album.
Access Terms
Branner, John Casper, 1850-1922.; Crandall, Berton W., 1882-1979.; Stanford University. Department of Athletics.; Stanford University. Student Army Training Corps.; Albums.; Photographers--California.; Photoprints.
Collection Contents
- 1904-1905 (Box 1)
- 1908-1909 (Box 2)
- 1909-1910 (Box 3)
- 1910-1911 (Box 4)
  Crowd scene in Palo Alto during T. Roosevelt's visit
- 1911-1912 (Box 5)
- 1909-1913 (Box 6)
  This volume is of individual athletes, yell leaders, and coaches; it also includes a photograph of Sam McDonald.
- 1913-1914 (Box 7)
  Branner's Inauguration as University President; Encina Hall's Annual Evening Dress Affair; bonfire; Lake Lagunita events; Skull & Snakes; graduation procession in Quad; a few women's events
- 1914-1915 (Box 8)
  Junior Day procession to the Mausoleum and other events; European Market in Palo Alto; Press Club initiation; bonfire; Lincoln Beachy flying plane around Berkeley Campanile; Skull & Snakes; graduation procession
- 1915-1916 (Box 9)
  European Market in Palo Alto; bonfire; student costume parade
- 1916-1917 (Box 10)
  Encina Hall residents on steps; Study Army Training Corps in Inner Quad, training in the hills, and marching in Palo Alto; Roughs Day
- 1917-1918 (Box 11)
  Dr. Stillman at train station; Major Pourie; Camp Fremont – barber, tents; Palo Alto Armory YCMA; Coach Wylie
- 1919-1920 (Box 12)
  [This volume is boxed with 1917-1918.] Swimmer Norman Ross; Airplane on campus (part of a sorority aviation party); Stanford ROTC; Armistice Parade in Palo Alto; Coach Evans
- 1920-1921 (Box 13)
- 1921-1922 (Box 14)
- 1923 (Box 15)
  Women's basketball game and track meet; polo and horsemanship contest; students working at Convalescent Home
- 1927 (Box 16)
- 1928-1929 (Box 17)
  Sports are basketball, baseball, track & field, and tennis.
- 1930 (Box 18)
  Sports are basketball, track & field, football, swimming, polo, and baseball.